All right בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today so we start today and
here with everybody in the scattered winds. We're going to do כו.
chaf vav. Today's דף daf is דף כו daf chaf vav and
we start at the very bottom of כה עמוד ב. chaf hey
amud bet. So we pick up with אמר אביי, amar Abaye, literally
the last few words. We might as well read from two lines
before that אמר רבא. amar Rava. So the question was the position
of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that says you
cannot use צרי, tzari, which is some type of aromatic oil, some
balsam oil. So why not? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so said
רבא, Rava, מתוך שריחו נודף mitoch she-reicho nodef because it's got a,
the, it's a very aromatic aroma and that's very powerful, גזירה שמא
יסתפק ממנו. gezeirah shema yistapek mimenu.
We're afraid that somebody is going to be so smell it and
be you know so desirous of it that they're going to dip
their bread into the oil and therefore indirectly cause the extinguishing of
the lamp or even if it doesn't extinguish right now, it will
burn for less of a time. So that's גרם כיבוי gram kibbuy
and therefore we do not allow you to do it. So אמר
ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so אביי Abaye said to him, top
now of כו עמוד א, chaf vav amud aleph, לימא מר מפני
שהוא עף. leima mar mipnei shehu af. Why are you saying that
the reason is because it's because it's because it smells so good,
how about the fact that it explodes? Meaning apparently sparks or ashes
or some parts of it will of the fire will float up
and adhere to the wall and the ceiling and it can set
your building on fire. So isn't that a concern? So it's interesting
רש"י Rashi says that so what's the problem that it'll set your
building on concern on fire? So תוספות Tosafot says, well the problem
is your building's on fire, you'll put out the fire on שבת.
Shabbos. But then תוספות Tosafot says, you know if that was true
we shouldn't allow you to do it during the weekday either. We
shouldn't let you do things that are going to put your building
on fire. But anyway so that's another reason. So the גמרא Gemara
says חדא ועוד קאמר, chada ve-od ka-amar,
one and another it's saying. חדא, chada, number one, מפני שהוא עף
mipnei shehu af because it floats and can catch fire to the
ceiling and the wall and that's a concern as I said maybe
even during the week. But regardless it certainly is a concern on
שבת. Shabbos. ועוד ve-od and another reason is גזירה שמא יסתפק ממנו,
gezeirah shema yistapek mimenu, we're concerned that you will come to dip
your bread in it and to benefit from it. So the גמרא
Gemara says ההיא חמתא, hahu chamata,
there was a mother-in-law דהוה סניא לה לכלתה, de-hava sania lah le-khaltah,
she hated her daughter-in-law. אמרה לה, amrah lah, she said to her,
זיל איקשיטי במשחא דאפרסמון. zil ikshiti bemishcha de-afarsimon.
Oh, you know, you should use this beautiful balsam oil to anoint
yourself with, to rub on your skin. It smells so nice. אזל
איקשט, azal itkshat, she went and she anointed herself or literally she
beautified herself. כי אתא אמרה לה, ki atah amrah lah, so when
she came to her mother-in-law, her mother-in-law said to her, you know
what, זיל אתלי שרגא. zil itli shraga. I need a light, can
you go light for me a candle? אזלה אתלה שרגא, azla itla
shraga, she went she lit a candle, אינפח בה נורא, infach bah
nura,
the light sort of lit on her, ואכלתה, ve-akhaltah, and it consumed
her. So very lovely little story there, obviously not something to be
to be emulated, but certainly a story that drives home the flammability
of this balsam oil. So good to take precautions. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues, ומדלות הארץ u-mi-dalot ha-aretz
now that we're talking about this balsam oil we digress a little
bit with some אגדתא. aggadata. ומדלות הארץ השאיר נבוזראדן רב טבחים לכורמים
וליוגבים. u-mi-dalot ha-aretz hishir Nevuzaradan Rav Tabachim le-khormim u-le-yogvim.
From the very poor of the land, this is in the destruction
of the first בית המקדש, Bais Hamikdash, נבוזראדן Nevuzaradan who was the
you know general, left over רב טבחים Rav Tabachim literally could mean
the head of the slaughterers, but the general, left over לכורמים וליוגבים
le-khormim u-le-yogvim for people to work the vines and for people to
work the land. So the גמרא Gemara is going to explain that
these were slightly differently. כורמים, kormim, what is כורמים kormim mean? תני
רב יוסף, tani Rav Yosef, אלו מלקטי האפרסמון מעין גדי ועד רמתא.
elu melaktei ha-afarsimon me-Ein Gedi ve-ad Ramata. These are the people that
gather up the balsam oil
from עין גדי Ein Gedi to רמתא. Ramata. So this is from
the word רש"י Rashi says כורם korem although כרם kerem is probably
one a way of reading that which is vine, it could also
mean to gather. So they're the gatherers of this balsam oil.
Okay they're also they're gatherers of this oil. And then it says
יוגבים yogvim and
יוגב yogave also somehow to mean to gather according to this, אלו
ציידי חלזון מסולמות של צור ועד חיפה elu tziyadei chilazon mi-sulamot shel
Tzur ve-ad Haifa or capture, these are the people that capture the
חלזון, chilazon, the snail from which we get תכלת tcheiles מסולמות של
צור mi-sulamot shel Tzur from the rises of צור Tzur ועד חיפה
ve-ad Haifa until חיפה Haifa which are all by of course the
the
the sea and therefore that's where they gather the snails from. Okay
so that was just a little bit of the side because of
the mention about the balsam oil. Now to continue, תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, our rabbis taught,
אין מדליקין בטבל טמא בחול, ein madlikin be-tevel tamei be-chol, you cannot
use. use non-kosher
טמא tamei טבל, tevel, טבל tevel is grain that has not had
תרומות terumas and מעשרות maasros taken from it, you cannot use it
on the weekday, even on the weekday, there is some problem, ואין
צריך לומר בשבת v'ein tzarich lomar b'shabbat certainly not on שבת, shabbat,
כיוצא בו keyotzei bo similarly, אין מדליקין בנפט ein madlikin b'neft you
cannot use naphtha, בין בלבן bein b'lavan
excuse me white naphtha, בחול b'chol on the weekday, ואין צריך לומר
בשבת v'ein tzarich lomar b'shabbat certainly not on שבת. shabbat. So these
are obviously more than just שבת shabbos concerns. What are the שבת
shabbos concerns? So the גמרא gemara says like this: בשלמא נפט לבן
bishlama neft lavan I understand this white naphtha מפני שהוא עף mipnei
shehu af for the reason we said before by this balsam oil,
it sort of floats and is flammable and if you use it
your building will catch on fire. So here by the way you
see that having good fire safety is already a concern of the
גמרא. gemara. אבל טבל טמא מאי טעמא aval tevel tamei mai taama
why can you not use טבל טמא? tevel tamei? If we learned
yesterday that you can use תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah and as you
destroy your תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah you can derive benefit from it,
so טבל טמא tevel tamei all it is is that it's grain
that has תרומה terumah still untaken from it. But if once you
take the תרומה terumah from it you can use טבל טמא tevel
tamei why should you not be able to use—you can use the
תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah to burn and to derive benefit, why should
you not be able to use the טבל טמא? tevel tamei? So
the גמרא gemara says why not? So it says מאי טעמא mai
taama so אמר קרא amar kra the פסוק pasuk says ואני הנה
נתתי לך את משמרת תרומתי. va'ani hinei natati l'cha es mishmeres terumosai.
I have given you the guarding of my תרומות terumos in the
plural, בשתי תרומות הכתוב מדבר bishtei terumos haksav midaber like we said
yesterday, talking about two תרומות, terumos, אחת תרומה טהורה ואחת תרומה טמאה,
achas terumah tehorah v'achas terumah temei'ah,
one טהורה tehorah and one טמאה. temei'ah. מה תרומה טהורה mah terumah
tehorah and now what we learned from that is that you have
to protect טהורה tehorah תרומה terumah from becoming טמאה temei'ah and that
טמאה temei'ah תרומה terumah you have to protect from people misusing it,
from not eating it and you have to burn it. And then
we learned another דרשה drasha that when you burn it you can
derive benefit. So what do we learn here? Here we learn the
following: מה תרומה טהורה אין לך בה אלא משעת הרמה ואילך mah
terumah tehorah ein l'cha bah ella mish'as harama v'eilach
the same way טהורה tehorah תרומה terumah you can only use from
the moment that you lift it up, meaning from the moment that
you separate it. A כהן kohen cannot eat טבל tevel and say,
oh look since I'm allowed to eat the תרומה terumah once it's
taken I can eat the טבל tevel that has the תרומה terumah
in it. No, you're not allowed to eat the תרומה terumah until
it is actually separated off from the grain. So the same way
that's true about the טהורה tehorah תרומה, terumah, אף תרומה טמאה af
terumah temei'ah even what I allowed you to benefit from the טמאה
temei'ah תרומה terumah which we learned yesterday was benefit during the process
of destroying, even that benefit אין לך בה אלא משעת הרמה ואילך
ein l'cha bah ella mish'as harama v'eilach is only once it is
separated and becomes separate תרומה. terumah. Once it is part of the
טבל tevel then it is off limits. Now by the way this
would seem to suggest if I can't burn טבל tevel and derive
benefit from it, it would seem to suggest that טבל tevel is
אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah
like we sort of said yesterday. The fact that I need a
special פסוק pasuk to tell me I can derive benefit from תרומה
טמאה terumah temei'ah when I burn it suggests that at the other
time—that otherwise תרומה טמאה terumah temei'ah is forbidden in benefit. And תוספות
tosafos had a whole discussion where we knew that from. So תוספות
tosafos here asks similarly do you mean to tell me that טבל
tevel is אסור בהנאה? assur b'hana'ah? We've never learned that. We never—it
never tells us that טבל tevel is אסור באכילה, assur b'achilah, we've
never learned that it's אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. So תוספות tosafos says
what we do know is what we learned from here is that
it's not true that it's אסור assur in הנאה hana'ah in general.
Let's say I don't know you want to roll around in your
טבל tevel or something like that, use it for bedding. That would
be allowed. What it is אסור assur for is אסור assur in
הנאה hana'ah that comes in the process of destroying it. So for
example you cannot feed טבל tevel to your animals or you cannot
burn טבל tevel and get the benefit. So it is not the
normal type of אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, it's quite interestingly. תרומה טמאה
terumah temei'ah is אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah except the הנאה hana'ah that
comes in the process of destroying, and טבל tevel is permissible בהנאה
b'hana'ah except for the הנאה hana'ah that comes in the process of
destroying it. So they're somewhat mirror images of one another. But it
is interesting as I
said that it is forbidden here in הנאה—I hana'ah mean excuse me
it is not forbidden in classic הנאה hana'ah it is forbidden in
הנאה hana'ah that you get in the process of destroying it. Okay
so now the גמרא gemara continues. גופא. gufa. Is everybody there? Can
people everybody hear me online?
Hello? Good. Yeah okay. גופא gufa so okay let's go back to
what we said before. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar omer, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar said, אין
מדליקין בצרי ein madlikin b'tzari
you cannot use צרי tzari this balsam oil for reasons we said,
either because it's aromatic or it sets the building on fire, whatever.
וכן היה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, v'chen hayah Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar omer, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar also used
to say another statement to be aware of if you're curious about
what this oil is. צרי אינו אלא שרף מעצי הקטף. tzari eino
ella saraf mei'atzei hakataph. צרי tzari
is—we say this in דאבנינג davening right when we talk about the
making of the what do you call it about the קטורת—צרי is
this שרף saraf this oil that comes from the balsam wood. Okay
so now the He's just telling you where it comes from. Now
some understand that he's not just mentioning parenthetically where it comes from,
but what he's actually doing is telling you the reason you can't
use it on שבת Shabbos because if it comes, if it's a
sap, sap as opposed to oils, do not burn smoothly and will
not be smoothly drawn after the wick. תוספות Tosafot says, you know,
if that's פשט, pshat, he doesn't understand why we're making up these
other reasons about that it's flammable or that it, or that it's
too aromatic. But anyway, he is pointing out here, whether as a
reason or just in general, that it is the sap of the
balsam tree. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says. Now רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says, כל היוצא מן העץ אין
מדליקין בו. kol hayotzei min ha'eitz ein madlikin bo. Anything that derives
from the tree, does not mean from fruit, but from wood, from
any other part of the tree you cannot use, presumably for this
reason, presumably because it does not draw well, it's not an oil
and doesn't draw well after the wick. רבי ישמעאל בן ברוקא, Rabbi
Yishmael ben Broka, a lot of שמעונים, Shimones, ישמעאלים, Yishmaels, רבי ישמעאל
בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael ben Broka says, אין מדליקין אלא ביוצא מן
הפרי. ein madlikin ela beyotzei min hapri. Not only can you just
not use stuff that comes from the wood, you can only use
stuff that comes from fruit, which means to exclude like the fish
oil. Okay, a lot of the things we mentioned were sesame oil
and olive oil, obviously those are things that come from various types
of fruits. Those are okay, but other things such as fish oil
or saps, those would be no good. So that's even stricter. רבי
טרפון אומר, Rabbi Tarfon omer, אין מדליקין אלא בשמן זית בלבד. ein
madlikin ela beshemen zayit bilvad. You can only use olive oil, olive
oil is the best, you can use nothing else. So you see
a slow movement to constantly add and add and add things on
the list that are forbidden until we get to the position that
you can only use olive oil. עמד רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא ועל
כל זאת. Amad Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka ve'al kol zot. רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka got up on his feet and
he said, ואמר, ve'amar, מה יעשו אנשי בבל שאין להם אלא שמן
שומשמין? mah ya'asu anshei Bavel she'ein lahem ela shemen shumshumin? You think
you're being so פרום, frum, you can only use olive oil, very
nice for you, but what are the people of בבל Bavel going
to do? They only have sesame oil, they don't have olive oil,
that's at least affordable. ומה יעשו אנשי מדי? u'mah ya'asu anshei Madai?
How about the people of מדי? Media? שאין להם אלא שמן אגוזים?
she'ein lahem ela shemen egozim? They only have nut oil. ומה יעשו
אנשי אלכסנדריא? u'mah ya'asu anshei Alexandria? What do you want the people
of אלכסנדריה Alexandria to do? שאין
להם אלא שמן צנונות? she'ein lahem ela shemen tzenonot? They only have
gourd oil. ומה יעשו אנשי קפודקיא? u'mah ya'asu anshei Kapotkia? What about
the people of קפודקיא? Kapotkia? שאין להם לא כך
ולא כך אלא נפט? she'ein lahem lo kach velo kach ela neft?
All they have is נפט. nefta. So you can't be, you know,
it's very nice that you're so פרום frum for your little community
that this thing works. But if you are really taking a responsibility
of leadership, then you're thinking about כל כלל ישראל kol Klal Yisrael
and you cannot make this ruling. אלא אין לך אלא מה שמנו
חכמים אין מדליקין. Ela ein lecha ela mah shemanu chachamim ein madlikin.
The only things that you can't list are things that the חכמים
Chachamim say you can't list. Now the question of course is, what
do you mean? You guys are the חכמים. Chachamim. But the obvious
point is, is that this is a, there was an earlier list
of the things you can't use and clearly came the later generations
and everybody wanted to add to the list. So comes רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says, excuse me, all you
have is the early list, you think you're being so פרום, frum,
you are actually making it impossible for people that do not have
other oils available. And this is the סתם stam position of the
משנה. Mishna. If you remember the משנה, Mishna, it started adding things
to the list, right? רבי ישמעאל אומר אין מדליקין בעיטרן מפני כבוד
השבת. Rabbi Yishmael omer ein madlikin be'itran mipnei kevod haShabbat. And then
it says, וחכמים מתירין בכל השמנים, veChachamim matirin bechol hashemanim, בשמן שומשמין
בשמן אגוזים, beshemen shumshumin beshemen egozim, right, the exact same oils that
were mentioned here by רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, sesame oil, nut oil,
בשמן צנונות, beshemen tzenonot, gourd oil, בשמן דגים בשמן פקועות בעיטרן ובנפט,
beshemen dagim beshemen paku'ot be'itran u'veneit, even עיטרן itran and נפט, neft,
which are these sort of smelly tars, all of that was the
חכמים Chachamim that are repeating in the stages and that's all he
says, מה שמנו חכמים. mah shemanu chachamim.
So again, there's this general statement of the חכמים Chachamim that is
a much more inclusive and then these other רבנים rabbis that are
trying to add more and more things to disallow. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says, ומדליקין, u'madlikin,
and not only that, בשמן דגים ובעיטרן, beshemen dagim u've'itran, just so
that there's no confusion, you know, you can even use the fish
oil and the עיטרן, itran, again the things that were mentioned in
the משנה Mishna that are allowed.
So where were we? רבי שמעון שזורי אומר, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri omer,
again, it's very interesting, you have רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Yishmael, רבי ישמעאל בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yishmael ben Broka, רבי שמעון
שזורי, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri, a lot of שינים shins here. רבי שמעון
שזורי אומר, Rabbi Shimon Shezuri omer, מדליקין בשמן פקועות ובנפט. madlikin beshemen
paku'ot u'veneit. Just to be clear also, you can use, and again
this is what's mentioned in the משנה, Mishna, you can use the
oil of gourds and this נפט. nefta. So now we're sort of
moving in the opposite direction. Before we were contracting, now we're moving
in the expanding direction and all of these are mentioned explicitly in
the משנה Mishna by the חכמים Chachamim that they are allowed. סומכוס
אומר, Sumchos omer,
סומכוס Sumchos says, okay, but just to be clear, כל היוצא מן
הבשר אין מדליקין בו אלא בשמן דגים. kol hayotzei min habasar ein
madlikin bo ela beshemen dagim. You cannot use anything that comes from
animal flesh, meat, you can use from fish, from fish. So basically
what's that saying? That's allowing fish oil and it's disallowing the sort
of liquefied fat which was on the early משנה Mishna that we
knew was not allowed. So also pretty consistent with what has been
the סתם stam position. So says the גמרא, Gemara, סומכוס היינו תנא
קמא, Sumchus hainu Tanna Kamma,
isn't that the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, meaning we just said, we
said that you can use everything except what the חכמים Chachamim say,
how is סומכוס Sumchus adding anything?
And חלב chelev was disallowed by the early sages as well, so
it's completely consistent. So איכא בינייהו דרב ברונא אמר רב ולא מסיימי.
itka beneihu d'Rav Bruna amar Rav v'lo mesaimei. This is the answer
the גמרא Gemara pulls out of its hat when it's trying to
find a distinction, which is the רב ברונא אמר רב, Rav Bruna
amar Rav, which רב ברונא אמר רב Rav Bruna amar Rav was
whether when you add kosher oils to the non-kosher ones does it
make it good or not. So that would be the debate. They
both say that animal fat is no good, but one of them
presumably would allow it with kosher oil mixed in, but it's just
ולא מסיימי, v'lo mesaimei, we don't know which is which. Okay, but
again quite interestingly, we have תנאים Tannaim coming and adding, adding, adding
things that are forbidden, and then רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon switching gears
and saying you guys are being way too strict and you go
back to the early position and then we start adding things or
clarifying all these things that are actually allowed. Okay. תניא רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר. Tanya, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer. Now רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar who we said before was the
one that said this who mentioned where this צרי tzari comes from,
where this balsam oil comes from, now he's going to tell us
something and mentioned that it came from a sap from a tree,
he's going to tell us another statement about things that are derived
from a tree. Let's take a look. So: תניא רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר כל היוצא מן העץ אין בו משום שלש על שלש
ומסככין בו חוץ מפשתן. Tanya, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer: kol hayotzei
min ha-etz ein bo mishum shalosh al shalosh u-masachin bo chutz mi-pishtan.
Anything that comes from a tree has no טומאה tumah of three
by three. Now, again, as I've mentioned before, you have to be
careful when it talks about טומאה tumah of garments, there are two
sizes: three by three אצבעות, etzba'ot, which is the width of a
finger, and three by three טפחים, tefachim, which is the width of
your whole hand, of your whole like handbreadth, which is four times
that. So three by three אצבעות etzba'ot is obviously very small, whatever
it is, it's maybe like three inches by three inches or smaller.
And that is considered a piece of cloth that only poor people
would care about. Rich people would throw it away. Three by three
טפחים, tefachim, which is more like nine inches by nine inches or
so or more, a foot by a foot, that's a piece of
cloth that everybody agrees has significance, even rich
people
would
care about that, everybody would agree is basically equivalent to a normal
garment. So a small little swath of three by three אצבעות etzba'ot
is the smallest size that something can become טמא, tamei, but even
that, not always clear because it's only small enough that it would
be cared for by poor people. Now, in order to know are
we talking about three by three טפחים tefachim or three by three
אצבעות, etzba'ot, you have to look. שלש, Shalosh, as people might know
in Hebrew, you use the opposite gender of the word for of
the number for the word that you are counting. So שלש shalosh
you use for feminine, so it's שלש אצבעות, shalosh etzba'ot, and שלשה
sheloshah you use for masculine words, so it's שלשה טפחים. sheloshah tefachim.
So it's really confusing when the text says ג' על ג', gimmel
al gimmel, you don't know what it's talking about. Anyway, here they
say שלש על שלש, shalosh al shalosh, which means three by three
fingers. So we're talking about a tiny little swath of cloth, and
we want to know, does it become טמא tamei if something טמא
tamei touches it? Is it considered enough of a garment?
So
it says that anything that comes from a tree, what are types
of things that come from a tree? So רש"י Rashi basically says
it would be like canvas or cotton. We normally would not have
put cotton there, but it means it grows from the
ground, considered to come from a tree. So if you make a
cloth out of those things, they do not become טמא tamei if
they're a small swath, if it's three by three, leaving open the
question about what if it's a big piece of cloth? What if
it's a whole garment? What if it's three טפחים tefachim by three
טפחים? tefachim? But at least a small swath does not become טמא,
tamei, this is not considered a classic type of a material. Classic
materials are wool and flax, not these things, linen. So therefore it
does not become טמא. tamei. And number two, ומסככין בו, u-masachin bo,
since it's a tree product and because it is not מקבל טומאה.
mekabel tumah. And that's just what we just said, what can you
use for סכך? schach? Something that number one grows from the ground,
so check, this grows from the ground. And number two, something that
does not become טמא. tamei. Well, we just said this isn't considered
a cloth, does not become טמא. tamei. So therefore you can use
this for סכך, schach, perfect. חוץ מפשתן. chutz mi-pishtan. What we're excluding
though is linen. Linen derives from a plant and that is considered
a cloth and that you can, because it's a cloth, you cannot
use it for סכך. schach. Okay, so that's what we're saying about
sort of materials that you use, garment materials that you get from
plant products. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, is that clear? Everybody with me?
Yep. Anybody there?
Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
so said אביי. Abaye. רבי שמעון אלעזר ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Shimon Elazar v'tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar and the תנא tana of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, of,
of,
from the house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, אמרו דבר אחד, amru
davar echad, they said the same thing. Where how do we know
this?
So,
so רבי שמעון אלעזר הא דאמרן, Rabbi Shimon Elazar hada amran, רבי
שמעון אלעזר Rabbi Shimon Elazar what we just said, this idea about
these canvas things and cotton not being considered a cloth. תנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל Tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael and the תנא tana from the
house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, again all these Shimons, רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Yishmael, it gets very confusing. מאי היא? Mai hi? What is
it? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא. brayta.
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
taught, הוה נאמרו בגדים בתורה סתם, hoveh ne'emru begadim b'Torah stam, the
Torah very often speaks about clothes. רש''י Rashi lists a lot of
places. When it talks about dead rodents it says if they touch
a בגד. beged. When it talks about a dead body it says
if it touches a בגד. beged. When it talks about a seminal
emission it says if it falls on a בגד. beged. When it
talks about ציצית tzitzis it talks about a בגד. beged. So what
constitutes clothes in the Torah? So you might say anything, anything that's
made for wear, but normally it says clothes normally without qualification. ופרט
לך הכתוב באחד מהן צמר ופשתים u'perat l'cha hakatuv b'echad mehen tzemar
u'fishtim
and in one time it says בבגד צמר או בבגד פשתים, b'beged
tzemar o b'beged pishtim, which is what? Which is on, which is
by צרעת. tzara'at. So therefore, by צרעת tzara'at it says that a
cloth, that by, you know, what we call leprosy, but anyway these
spots, it says a garment of צמר tzemar or of פשתים. fishtim.
And therefore it says ופרט לך הכתוב u'perat l'cha hakatuv of by
wool or
linen, מה להלן צמר ופשתים אף כל צמר ופשתים. mah halan tzemar
u'fishtim af kol tzemar u'fishtim. That is to tell you that normal
that when we say clothes, we mean something made of wool and
linen. One place in the Torah it says clothes of wool and
clothes of linen, a garment of wool, a garment of linen. So
rather than saying that's a limitation, we are saying that that serves
as the paradigm, that a garment means something made out of wool
or linen. בגד צמר או... Beged tzemar o...
so therefore, let's take a look. So מה להלן צמר ופשתים? mah
halan tzemar u'fishtim?
So the same way by צרעת tzara'at it means only wool or
linen, אף כל צמר ופשתים, af kol tzemar u'fishtim, all clothes are
only wool or linen. So therefore you just excluded things that grow
from the ground. Says אביי, Abaye, I'm assuming you don't just mean
to exclude cotton. Why should you exclude cotton more than other things?
What you're really doing is you're excluding anything that is not wool
and linen. So this teaching of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar is the same as the teaching of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, anything that is not wool and linen does not count as
a garment. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, שלשה על שלשה
בשאר בגדים איכא בינייהו. shlosha al shlosha bish'ar begadim ika beinaihu.
No, it's not exactly the same position. There's a difference about what
if it's a large garment. Remember all רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar said is that three by three אצבעות etzba'ot does
not count. If it's a tiny swath, that suggests that if it's
a large garment, maybe these are sort of considered second-grade materials. So
small swaths don't count, but maybe large garments do. So he says
they're not the exact same. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says anything that
is not wool and linen does not count at all. רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar just said it doesn't count for
a small swath. But if it's a big piece, three by three
טפחים tfachim then it does count. Okay, that's reasonable because why else
would he even mention a small swath? So רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
אית ליה Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar itlei לתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל l'tana
d'bei Rabbi Yishmael אית ליה, itlei, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar says that would be a garment if it's a big
piece even if it's made of like cotton. לתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל
לית ליה l'tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael leitlei and the תנא tana from
the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says no, absolutely anything that's
not wool and linen does not count. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, דכולי עלמא מיהא, d'chulei alma miha, so whether אביי, Abaye,
אביי Abaye says they say the exact position, it doesn't matter if
it's a tiny piece, doesn't matter if it's a large piece, not
wool and linen doesn't count, and רבא Rava says actually if it's
a big piece for one of the opinions, for רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar that would count as a garment. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
where were we? Okay. דכולי עלמא מיהא, D'chulei alma miha,
everyone nevertheless would agree that שלשה על שלשה בצמר ופשתים מיטמי בנגעים.
shlosha al shlosha b'tzemar u'fishtim metamei b'nega'im. That at least that when
you do have a classic garment of wool or linen, then even
a small size of three by three fingers would become טמא. tamei.
Where do you get that from? The תורה Torah only mentions a
בגד. beged. How do you know a small little swath? Before you
go excluding other material, how do you know to include a tiny
little swath of three by three fingers? So מנלן? minalan? Where do
you know that from? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: brayta:
בגד, beged, again it says by צרעת tzara'at if it touch if
you have a leprosy a spot on a בגד. beged. אין לי
אלא בגד, ein li ela beged, I only know a full garment.
שלשה על שלשה מנלן? shlosha al shlosha minalan? How do I know
three by three finger-widths, a tiny little swath can become טמא? tamei?
תלמוד לומר והבגד, talmud lomar v'ha-beged,
and the garment. So the 'and' is saying even something that is
just like a little swath that you would use to like, you
know, as a patch, even that counts. And somehow of course that
doesn't tell you three by three. But okay, that already the rabbis
in the end get to say exactly what the size is. But
the והבגד v'habeged is telling you it doesn't have to really represent
the garment, it could even be a piece of a garment, something
used as a swath. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא לרבות שלוש
על שלוש, v'eima l'rabot shalosh al shalosh, but how do you know
to go all the way down to a little swath? Maybe it's
שלוש על שלוש טפחים, shalosh al shalosh tefachim, which is a significant
size, which could actually be a garment in its own terms. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, that you wouldn't need a פסוק. pasuk.
לאו קל וחומר הוא? lav kal v'chomer hu? It's a קל וחומר
kal v'chomer that a big piece should become טמא. tamei. Why is
it a קל וחומר? kal v'chomer?
It can't be a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from a full garment,
but here's the קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. השתא שתי וערב מיטמא שלוש
על שלוש מיבעיא? hashta shati v'erev mitamei shalosh al shalosh mibaia? The
תורה Torah says something very strange
by צרעת. tzara'at. It says not only does a garment become טמא,
tamei, but it even says
that the warp and the woof become טמא tamei even if it's
not woven into a garment. You have a spindle of warp or
a spindle of woof and it gets a blemish of צרעת, tzara'at,
that can become טמא, tamei, even not a garment. The only time
this is true is by צרעת, tzara'at, it's not true by other
טומאות. tumot. So now it says look, if warp and woof become
טמא, tamei, those things aren't a garment at all, so certainly something
that already is a big שלוש על שלוש טפחים, shalosh al shalosh
tefachim, that's something it's a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Now of course
it's not exactly a linear
comparison. Warp and woof could be woven into a full garment, how
much warp, how much woof, but anyway that's what the גמרא Gemara
is saying. If something that's not a garment at all, then certainly
שלוש על שלוש טפחים, shalosh al shalosh tefachim, we do not need
a פסוק pasuk for that. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי
שלוש על שלוש נמי ליתי בקל וחומר? ei hachi shalosh al shalosh
nami lisei b'kal v'chomer? Fine, so then say even three fingers by
three fingers. If warp and woof become טמא, tamei, then three fingers
by three fingers should become טמא, tamei, because that's at least woven
into something. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אלא הכא שלוש על
שלוש דחזו בין לעניים בין לעשירים, ela hacha shalosh al shalosh dechazu
bein l'aniyim bein l'ashirim, בין לעשירים בין לעניים. bein l'ashirim bein l'aniyim.
This is what I told you before, that שלוש על שלוש טפחים
shalosh al shalosh tefachim is already something that even a rich person
would not throw out. You figure out something to use it for.
You'd make a scarf out of it. It's not a patch, it
can actually be a garment. So that it's a universal use, אתי
בקל וחומר. ati b'kal v'chomer. Then if warp and woof are טמא,
tamei, certainly something that's שלוש על שלוש טפחים shalosh al shalosh tefachim
that anybody would use in some way as some type of a
garment and it's already woven, certainly that could become טמא. tamei. That
you could learn from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. שלוש
על שלוש, shalosh al shalosh, but three by three fingers, that what
is that? That's a patch, that's not a garment. That's a little
swath. דלעניים הוא דחזי לעשירים לא חזי. de'l'aniyim hu dechazi l'ashirim lo
chazi. It's only fit for poor, not fit for rich people. לא
אתי בקל וחומר. lo ati b'kal v'chomer. It's not a קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. Warp and woof might be more significant. Warp and woof
you could make into a real garment that even rich people would
want. A little swath three by three fingers, rich people would throw
out, so there's no קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. So now what has
the גמרא Gemara said? Before we get on to other material, how
do we know that small sizes are not full garments are טמא?
tamei? So since we find out that warp and woof are טמא,
tamei, we find out that it's a קל וחומר kal v'chomer that
something that's a big enough size that anybody would want to use,
even rich people, that's טמא tamei as well. So שלוש על שלוש
טפחים, shalosh al shalosh tefachim, which could be used for some type
of a garment, everybody would say that's טמא tamei or could become
טמא tamei the same way warp and woof. How do we know
even three by three fingers, which is only good enough to use
for a patch? That you learn from an extra פסוק והבגד. pasuk
v'habeged. All of this we say by צרעת tzara'at and presumably once
we say it by צרעת, tzara'at, we're going to apply it to
other places of טומאה tumah of cloth as well. Although interestingly some
of this we learn from the fact of a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer from warp and woof. Warp and woof is not true by
other טומאות, tumot, it's only true by צרעת. tzara'at. But once we
learn in צרעת tzara'at that garments שלוש על שלוש טפחים shalosh al
shalosh tefachim or even three by three fingers can become טמא, tamei,
we will apply it to other places as well. Okay, so that's
what we know by צרעת tzara'at and that's what we know by
wool and linen. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on. So the
גמרא Gemara says like
this. טעמא דכתב קרא הא לא כתב קרא. ta'ama dechtav kra ha
lo chtav kra. So the reason you know three by three fingers
is because the תורה Torah wrote it by והבגד. v'habeged. Had the
תורה Torah not written it, לא גמרינן בקל וחומר. lo gamrinan b'kal
v'chomer. You just got through telling me I could not have made
a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, that I needed the words והבגד v'habeged
to tell me three by three fingers. Okay, ואימא לרבות שלוש על
שלוש בשאר בגדים. v'eima l'rabot shalosh al shalosh b'shar bgadim.
So now we have this, what do we know? We know by
צרעת tzara'at wool and linen, and we know שלוש על שלוש טפחים
shalosh al shalosh tefachim based on a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Comes
along this extra phrase והבגד v'habeged and the garment. So what do
you come to include? You said you come to include even a
swath, even three by three fingers. Says the גמרא, Gemara, why go
that way? Why not come to include other material? Why are you
moving down in size, even small sizes? Why not, if we want
to include things that are טמא, tamei, don't we expand the materials
and say don't limit yourself to wool and linen? ואימא לרבות שאר
בגדים. ve'eima lerabot she'ar begadim. How about other types of garments? Reasonable
question. So אמר קרא, amar kra, says no, the גמרא Gemara says,
בגד צמר או פשתים. beged tzemer o pishtim. בגד צמר או פשתים,
beged tzemer o pishtim, אין מידי אחריני לא. in midei achrinei lo.
It says no, it's clear, it says wool and linen, just wool
and linen. Says the גמרא, Gemara, one minute, ואימא כי אמעיט משלוש
על שלוש. ve'eima ki ameit mishalosh al shalosh. Okay, I get that
wool and linen is something special, but maybe we'll say it this
way: a tiny little swath that's three by three fingers, that is
only when it's made out of a classic garment, of a classic
material, wool and linen. Then a small swath matters, three by three.
אבל שלושה
על שלושה, aval shlosha al shlosha, but maybe if you have a
big size, שלושה על שלושה טפחים, shlosha al shlosha tefachim, then מטמא,
metamei, then it should become טמא tamei even if it's other material.
So the גמרא Gemara isn't giving up. I still want to say
והבגד, vehabeged, maybe from והבגד, vehabeged, maybe elsewhere, I want to include
other materials. You're telling me why then does the תורה Torah mention
wool and linen? Okay, so wool and linen are special, even small
sizes. But at least when it comes to the big sizes of
three by three טפחים, tefachim, at least that should be okay with,
or not okay, it should be considered a garment with other materials.
Reasonable question. So the גמרא Gemara says, תרי מיעוטי כתיבי. terei miutei
ktivi. No, it says it twice,
wool and linen. בגד צמר או בבגד פשתים. beged tzemer o beveged
pishtim. It says, it says two פסוקים, psukim, one בגד צמר ופשתים,
beged tzemer upishtim, one בבגד צמר או בבגד פשתים. beveged tzemer o
beveged pishtim. It says twice, it underscores wool and linen. חד למיעוטי
משלוש על שלוש וחד למיעוטי משלושה על שלושה. chad lemiutei mishalosh al
shalosh vechad lemiutei mishlosha al shlosha. One to tell you that if
it's not wool and linen, even three- it doesn't become טמא tamei
if it's a swath, and one to tell you if it's not
wool and linen, it does not become טמא tamei even if it
is a, even if it is a large size, three by three
טפחים, tefachim, and presumably also even if it is a full garment.
Okay, so where are we now? We have seen by- by צרעת
tzaraat that the תורה Torah mentions wool and linen, and it has
an extra והבגד. vehabeged. Also, we know warp and woof. Based on
the combination of warp and woof and a קל וחומר kal vachomer
and the והבגד, vehabeged, we come to the conclusion that you don't
need a full garment, even three by three טפחים, tefachim, not only
that, even three by three fingers. But only wool and linen, because
the תורה Torah repeats wool and linen, wool and linen, only wool
and linen, nothing else. So that, if we use that as the
paradigm, that gets you to the conclusion of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
which is that wool and linen matter- only wool and linen count
as a garment for everything in the תורה, Torah, nothing else counts.
However, we are also seeing laying the groundwork for רבא's Rava read
of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, that there's a
difference between three fingers and three טפחים. tefachim. Three fingers might be
limited to wool and linen, because which is again a classic material.
Three טפחים, tefachim, which is a larger size, maybe the exclusion doesn't
apply there, and maybe there other material does count. So let's just
be- read that and we'll begin that and finish this tomorrow. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולרבא דאמר שלושה על שלושה בשאר
בגדים איכא בינייהו. ulerava de'amar shlosha al shlosha bishe'ar begadim ika beineihu.
So רבא, Rava, who I just said says the difference between רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
is that according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar,
if it is three by three טפחים, tefachim, then even other materials
count as a garment. So רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אית ליה, Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar it lei, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar says that would count as a garment even by other materials.
ולתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל לית ליה, uletana devei Rabbi Yishmael leit lei,
and the תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael does not
hold of it. So שלושה על שלושה בשאר בגדים מנא ליה? shlosha
al shlosha bishe'ar begadim minalei? So where does he know this idea
that in other- by other materials three by three טפחים tefachim matters?
So as I said, we sort of already laid the groundwork about
that by, you know, discussing maybe that's what the פסוק pasuk is
coming to do is to include other materials. But let's see what
the גמרא Gemara answers. Top of כז עמוד א. Kaf Zayin Amud
Aleph. So מנא ליה, minalei, where does he know that other materials
do matter if it's big enough? נפקא מאו בגד. nafka me'o beged.
The פסוק pasuk says או בגד, o beged, or a garment, which
is in an או בגד, o beged, the או o is considered
to be- to come somehow including, and therefore what's it including? It
is including that there are other types of material. So how do
you balance the fact that some פסוקים psukim said only wool and
linen and other פסוקים psukim are seen to include other material? You
make the split between whether it is three by three fingers, which
is only wool and linen, or three by three טפחים, tefachim, which
is other material. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Beraita, we'll
just read this: בגד, beged, a garment. אין לי אלא בגד
שלושה על שלושה בשאר בגדים מניין? ein li ela beged shlosha al
shlosha bishe'ar begadim minayin? I only know a full garment. שלושה על
שלושה בשאר בגדים מניין, shlosha al shlosha bishe'ar begadim minayin, how do
I know three טפחים tefachim by three טפחים tefachim by non-wool and
linen garments? תלמוד לומר או בגד, talmud lomar o beged, or garments.
So that is how we are learning, at least according to רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, we are learning that other
garments do count if they're big enough. I should mention that besides
טומאה וטהרה, tumah vetaharah, this has a big נפקא מינה nafka mina
for other things, like as I mentioned earlier, one place it mentions
בגד beged is ציצית. tzitzit. So if you have a full garment
made out of made a full garment out of cotton is it
חייב chayav in ציצית tzitzis biblically or not? It's a big מחלוקת
machlokes מחלוקת machlokes in the גמרא Gemara מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes rishonim מחלוקת
machlokes how we פוסקין paskin right? And that is exactly this issue.
When we are saying wool and linen are special, are they only
special because okay for like small little swaths only wool and linen,
but a full garment of three by three טפחים tefachim other material
as well? That's the way רבא Rava reads רבי שמעון בן אלעזר.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar. Or do we say no like רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael wool and linen count nothing else count and אביי Abaye
that even agreed to by רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar. So this is a debate that has implications beyond טומאה. tumah.
Let's just read אביי's Abaye response and we'll end with that for
today. ואביי האי או בגד מאי עביד ליה? V'Abaye hai O Beged
mai avid lei? According to אביי Abaye that even רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says anything that's not wool and linen
doesn't matter, what does he do with
או בגד? O Beged? מיבעי ליה לרבות שלש על שלש בצמר ופשתים
דמטמא בשרצים. Mibaye lei l'rabos shalosh al shalosh b'tzemer u'fishtim d'mitamei b'shratzim.
He says ah what we have to do now is we have
to now we've proven everything we need to say by צרעת tzaraas
that it's only wool and linen but even three by three fingers
fine we've proven that. But how do we know now say that
that applies to all other טומאות? tumos? How do we use that
as a paradigm? That's what או בגד O Beged teaches me. So
we do not other materials don't count at all. או בגד O
Beged is not including other materials. It's coming to apply this definition
of a garment to all other areas of טומאה tumah even to
the טומאה tumah of dead rodents. ורבא, V'Rava, how does רבא Rava
learn to apply it? גלי רחמנא גבי נגעים והוא הדין לשרצים. Galei
Rachmana gabei negaim v'hu hadin l'shratzim.
It's a paradigm the Torah tells you that this is true by
צרעת tzaraas and that then serves as a model for all other
טומאות. tumos. You don't need a פסוק. pasuk. ואביי, V'Abaye, what would
אביי Abaye say why do you need a פסוק? pasuk? איכא למיפרך
מה לנגעים שכן שתי וערב מטמא בהם. Ika l'mifrach mah l'negaim sheken
shesi v'erev mitamei bahem.
That by נגעים negaim as we said one of the ways we
learn out and derived one of the ways we learn out certain
aspects of garments is the fact that warp and woof are טמא
tamei by צרעת tzaraas and by nothing else. So since that's one
of the ways we learn some of this stuff out you cannot
apply the garments by צרעת tzaraas to other places. Other places is
maybe even a smaller definition who knows what we say by other
places? So that's why you needed the extra פסוק או בגד pasuk
O Beged to apply from צרעת tzaraas to other places. ואידך, V'idach,
and what would רבא Rava say back? That's a very good point.
How can we just assume it's a paradigm? No. אי סלקא דעתך
נגעים חמירי, Isalka daatach negaim chamiri, if נגעים negaim were stricter and
the rule did not apply elsewhere then the very interesting argument ליכתוב
רחמנא גבי שרצים וליתי נגעים מינייהו. lichtov Rachmana gabei shratzim v'lesei negaim
minaihu.
It's like a type of thing the גמרא Gemara could always say.
You can't learn this out it's a stricter category. Well if it
didn't want me to learn it out if you think it's a
stricter category it should have written it by a more by you
know by the more lenient category. Now of course you can only
say that once you know the Torah is trying to expand it.
So that's what so that's anyway but that's what רבא Rava is
saying. רבא Rava is saying is if או בגד O Beged were
coming to extend it we all agree it does apply to נגעים.
negaim. If או בגד O Beged were coming to extend it to
נגעים negaim then the Torah would not have done then the Torah
would have just made it life easier and written it by שרצים.
shratzim. That would have got the same result of expanding it. The
fact that the Torah didn't write it by שרצים shratzim to me
I lost my train of thought I'm sorry. If the Torah we
know רבא Rava says I know from
hold on how's it going I know this is serving as a
paradigm. You אביי Abaye want to and you learn it to שרצים.
shratzim. You אביי Abaye want to say you learn it to שרצים
shratzim from או בגד O Beged and you say you can't learn
it from נגעים negaim because נגעים negaim is more strict. Well then
according to you אביי Abaye why did the Torah write it by
נגעים negaim and say או בגד? O Beged? It should have just
written it by שרצים. shratzim. So therefore I come to the conclusion
that it's not more strict you don't need או בגד O Beged
then it would have written by שרצים shratzim and או בגד O
Beged is extra and that tells you other material. And what does
אביי Abaye say back?
So אביי Abaye says back one minute where were we? ואידך נגעים
משרצים לא אתו. V'idach negaim mishratzim lo asu. No the Torah could
not have written it by rodents and learned it from a קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. You needed a פסוק pasuk to extend. Why not?
דאיכא למיפרך מה שרצים שכן מטמא בעדשה. D'ika l'mifrach mah shratzim sheken
mitamei b'adasha.
שרצים shratzim have a way that they are strict as well. שרצים
shratzim are טמא tamei even if it is the size of a
little עדשה adasha lentil bean other things need a larger size. So
therefore says אביי Abaye look the Torah had to write it in
one and use a פסוק pasuk to write it in the other
because each one has its own stringencies. So therefore I am going
to say it wrote it by נגעים negaim and או בגד O
Beged is coming to extend it to other cases of טומאה. tumah.
Because wherever the Torah would have written it it would have needed
a פסוק pasuk to extend it elsewhere. And in the end says
אביי Abaye what I learn from נגעים negaim is just wool and
linen absolutely nothing else. And רבא Rava says no I assume if
it's written in one area you can apply it to the other
area. What do I learn from או בגד? O Beged? I learn
to include material that is not wool and linen at least if
it's of a larger size. So just to wrap that up that
was A little complicated, but to wrap that up, we have רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that clearly says anything that's not wool and linen
doesn't matter, no matter how big it is, and that has big
implications for טומאה Tumah and for ציצית Tzitzit and similar. Then we
have רב שמעון בן אלעזר, Reb Shim Ben Elazar, who says, who's
a little cryptic. אביי Abaye interprets him like רבי ישמעאל; Rabbi Ishmael;
according to both of them, if it's not wool and linen, it
doesn't count. And רבא Rava says, according to him, a large size,
three by three טפחים tfachim would count of other material. How do
you get this? From צרעת Tzara'at we all agree, wool and linen
is what is emphasized, and even a small size. And then the
question becomes, what do you learn from או בגד? O Beged? Does
או בגד O Beged come to expand it to other types of
טומאות, tumot, or do we say that we would know by ourselves,
and או בגד O Beged is coming to say that other material,
if it's a larger size, does matter? And that is the way
רבא Rava reads רב שמעון בן אלעזר. Reb Shim Ben Elazar. So
we will continue with this debate tomorrow. Everybody should please stay safe
and, yeah, and stay warm and if we need to we will
continue tomorrow virtually as we did today as well. Okay, take care
everybody, bye.